A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Harry E. Wilhelm FA628
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Harry E. Wilhelm
1965-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA628
3.52 Cubic Feet
These papers from the Office of Harry E. Wilhelm cover the years 1965 to 1970, while Mr. Wilhelm was the New York-based Director of the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean. They are arranged in three series. Access to two of the three series is restricted to internal staff use because these series contain personnel-related material. The papers consist primarily of chronological files and confidential correspondence. Also included in the papers is some of Wilhelm's chronological files that were retained by his Senior Staff Assistant [1966 - 1967?], Catharine A. Olson. She used the initials "CAPO" to identify the files which she maintained.
Biographical / Historical
Harry E. Wilhelm, Director of the Latin American and Caribbean Program from February 1965 to December 1970, also held the following positions at the Foundation:
• January 1971, Representative, India and Nepal • February 1963, Representative, Argentina and Chile • October 1961, Program Associate, South and Southeast Asia Program • October 1959, Assistant Representative, Burma • November 1957, Assistant to the Representative, Burma
(N.B.: In Jan 1967, the program organizaton of the Foundation was restructured. At this time, the Latin America and Caribbean Program became part of the International Division. Wilhelm's title was changed to Head, Latin America and the Caribbean).
On December 18, 1975 Wilhelm resigned from the Foundation.
Harry E. Wilhelm was born on August 21, 1928. He received his A.B. in Political Science and English from Ohio Wesleyan University and his M.P.A. in Public & International Affairs from the Woodrow Wilson School of Public & International Affairs at Princeton University.
Prior to joining the Foundation, Wilhelm held several positions in the Executive Office of the President of the United States' Bureau of the Budget. In 1969, while Head of the Foundation's Latin American and Caribbean Program, Wilhelm served on evaluation committees of the Organization of American States and of the National Academy of Sciences, respectively.
Scope and Contents
These papers from the Office of Harry Wilhelm cover the years 1965 to 1970, during which time Mr. Wilhelm was Director of the Latin American and Caribbean (LAC) program in New York. They are divided into three series. Series I, CHRONOLOGICAL FILES, contains Mr. Wilhelm's copy of his correspondence to persons outside the Foundation, as well as his copy of his correspondence, memoranda and telegrams to Ford Foundation staff. This series is available to all researchers. Series II, CONFIDENTIAL CORRESPONDENCE, contains inter-office memoranda, correspondence, telexes and telegrams. Series III, "CAPO CONFIDENTIAL" CHRONOLOGICAL FILES, are Wilhelm's 1966 to 1967 chronological files that were retained by Catherine A. Olson, Mr. Wilhelm's Senior Staff Assistant. Access to Series II and III is available to internal staff only, and only with the permission of the Archivist, because these series contain sensitive personnel-related material. It should be noted that within the three series there is a fair amount of duplicate material. These duplicates have been kept in the folders so as to maintain the papers in the order in which they were received by the Archives.
Arrangement
The Latin America and Caribbean Papers of Harry E. Wilhelm, are divided into three series:
I. Chronological Files, March 1966 to April 1970, consists of 2' of material.
II. Confidential Correspondence, February 1965 - December 1970, consists of 1' of material.
III. "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, April 1966 - February 1967, consists of .5' of material.
Separated Materials
Papers falling into the following categories were removed from all three series and placed with the appropriate files in the Ford Foundation Archives:
• Staff and consultant reports • Annual reports on the activities of the LAC program • Budget papers
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Chronological Files, 1966-1970; I
  Arrangement
  Series I, Chronological Files (March 1966 to April 1970), is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Chronological Files, consists of Wilhelm's copy of his outgoing correspondence to persons outside the Foundation, as well as his copy of his correspondence to Foundation staff and of his memoranda to the files. The material in this series provides an overview of the Foundation's interests in Latin America and the Caribbean for the years 1965 to 1970, and demonstrates that one of the Foundation's overriding goals in Latin America was to improve the caliber of higher education throughout the region. There are memoranda concerning the 1965 grant (PA65-327) to the International Institute of Education to strengthen the University of Chile through an exchange program with the University of California. Another dominant Foundation interest was agricultural development. There are memoranda and discussion outlines which document the early stages of the Foundation's collaboration with the Rockefeller Foundation in the development of international agricultural centers in Latin America (Log 66-88). This series also contains material concerning the Action Committee for Latin American Integration (Log 67-210). There is some memoranda concerning the involvement of the late Senator Jacob Javits in this project. Material relating to personnel policies, administrative procedures, fiscal year program budgets, and overall program planning for the LAC office is also filed in this series.
  - Chronological Files, 1970 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 February 27 - 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 February 16 - 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 September 30 - 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 September 15 - 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 August (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 May 29 - 16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 May 15 - 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 April 30 - 16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 April 15 - 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 March 28 - 11 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 March 10 - 3 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 February 28 - 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 February 20 - 3 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 January 31 - 17 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 January 16 - 2 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 December (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 November (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 October 31 - 15 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 October 14 - 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 September 30 - 17 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 September 12 - 3 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 August 30 - 19 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 August 16 - 1 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 July 31 - 15 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 July 12 - 1 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 June (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 May 29 - 15 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 May 14 - 1 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 April 30 - 19 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 April 18 - 1 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 March 29 - 13 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 March 12 - 1 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 February (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 January 31 - 16 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 January 15 - 2 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 December (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 November 30 - 16 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 November 15 - 1 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 October (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 September (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 August (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 July 31 - 16 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 July 14 - 5 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 June 30 - 12 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 June 9 - 1 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 May 31 - 16 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 May 15 - 1 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 April 28 - 17 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 April 14 - 3 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 March (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 February 20 - 14 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 February 13 - 1 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 January (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 December (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 November (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 October 31 - 20 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 October 19 - 3 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 September 30 - 16 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 September 16 - 1 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 August 31 - 16 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 August 15 - 1 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 July (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 June 30 - 16 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 June 15 - 2 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 May (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 April (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 March (Box 5, Folder 75)
- Confidential Correspondence, 1965-1970; II
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series II Confidential Correspondence is restricted from scholarly research. All contents of this series is closed.
  Series II, Confidential Correspondence (February 1965 - December 1970), is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  The bulk of Series II, Confidential Correspondence, is the inter-office memoranda that were exchanged among Mr. Wilhelm in New York, and the Foundation's field office staffs in Latin America and the Caribbean. These memoranda deal primarily with the organization and staffing of the LAC program, and include a considerable amount of personnel-related information such as staff evaluations and salary recommendations. Roughly one quarter of the inter-office correspondence in this series duplicates the grantee-related inter-office correspondence in Series I, Chronological Files.
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 December 10 - August 24 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    Restricted from scholarly research.
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 August 12 - May 1 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 April 21 - February 9 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 January 31 - 5 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 December 24 - July 1 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 June 27 - May 1 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 April 30 - February 17 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 January 24 - 3 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 December 27 - September 4 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 August 30 - 6 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 July 25 - May 8 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 April 17 - January 31 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 December 28 - September 8 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 August 22 - June 5 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 May 31 - April 14 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 April 3 - January 17 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 December 20 - October 4 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 September 27 - June 6 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 May 30 - April 1 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 March 17 - January 4 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 December 17 - October 1 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 September 23 - 4 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 July 30 - May 3 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 April 28 - February 4 (Box 7, Folder 99)
- "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966-1967; III
  Series III, "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files (April 1966 - February 1967), is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Series III is restricted from scholarly research. All contents of this series is closed.
  Series III, "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, consists of copies of that portion of Mr. Wilhelm's 1966 to 1967 outgoing correspondence which was deemed confidential or personal by his Senior Staff assistant, Catharine A. Olson. This series contains 1967 and 1968 program budget and planning material, as well as material relating to the Overseas Development Self Study, conducted in the fall of 1966. Almost one half of the material in this series duplicates the material in Series II.
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1967 April 3 - February 2 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1967 January 30 - 5 (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 December 22 - 2 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 October 31 - 4 (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 September 30 - August 4 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 July 20 - May 2 (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 April 25 - February 28 (Box 8, Folder 106)
- Appendix A: Material Removed
  The following list of unpublished reports written by FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers and transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports. The reports are listed alphabetically by author. The number at the left is the assigned accession number.
  The list of four reports that follows the first list were removed from the papers and transferred to the Archives collection of annual reports from and about the activities of the Foundation's field offices. These reports are located in the Vital Records Room.
  The last report listed was removed from the papers and transferred to binder #9 of the Archives collecton of budget papers. These papers are located in the Vital Records Room.
  - Adams, Richard N. Research on Migration and Adaptation (Report 3209)
  - Angulo, Carlos and Hunt, Shane. The Ford Foundation in Peru, 1969 June (Report 9463)
  - Barrett, Laurence N. (Ford Foundation Education Programs in Chile), 1965 August 17 (Report 1417)
  - Bell, David. The International Division - General Shape and Content, 1966 October (Report 118)
  - Bundy, McGeorge. The Nature and Meaning of a $200 Million Budget, 1967 March 16 (Report 1009)
  - Finberg, Donald. Chilean Taxes, 1965 June (Report 9932)
  - Finberg, Donald. Highlights of Weekly Activities of the Santiago Sub-Office, April 12 through April 17, 1965 April (Report 10079)
  - Ford Foundation Staff. (Memoranda re Argentina, 1966), 1966 October (Report 7818)
  - Ford Foundation Staff. (Summaries of Ford Foundation in Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Peru, Uruguay, and Venezuela) (Report 9806)
  - Hilliard, John F. Caribbean Office, 1968 March (Report 10162)
  - Keegan, Frank L. Notes Toward a Study of the Latin American University, 1967 March (Report 9804)
  - Lowenthal, Abraham F. Peru's Current Situation, 1969 December (Report 5614)
  - Lowenthal, Abraham F. Six Weeks in Peru: Some First Impressions, 1969 October 25 (Report 4191)
  - Manitzas, Nita Rous. (The Torcuato Di Tella Institute), 1967 November 28 (Report 704)
  - Nelson, Courtney A. Overseas Compensation Study, 1969 June (Report 9805)
  - Silvert, Kalman H. Report on trip to Jamaica, 1968 February (Report 5906)
  - Trowbridge, James W. OD-LA Population Program - Notes for Discussion at Representatives' Meeting, New York, August 4, 1966, 1966 September 19 (Report 69)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Andean Universities, 1969 January (Report 8722)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Future Program Plans for the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean, 1970 January 21 (Report 4655)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Notes on the Ford Foundation's Activities in Population, 1968 January 31 (Report 9736)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Report and Recommendations on Support Budgets and other Supporting Projects of the International Division, 1967 July 5 (Report 118)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Some Issues Concerning the Future of the Ford Foundation, 1970 January 26 (Report 4500)
  - Wilhelm, Harrry E. University of Chile - University of California Collaboration (PA65-327), 1968 January (Report 4824)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Activities in Latin America and the Caribbean, Fisal Year 1966, 1966 October 25 (Report -)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Activities of the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean, Fiscal Year 1967, 1967 November 20 (Report -)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Activities of the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean in 1968, 1969 January 7 (Report -)
  - Wilhelm, Harry E. Office for Latin America and the Caribbean, Report on 1969, 1970 January 10 (Report -)
  - OLAC. Fiscal Year 1966 Program Budget, 1966 July (Report -)
- Appendix B: Ford Foundation LAC Field Office Staff, 1965-1970
  Appendix B: Ford Foundation LAC Field Office Staff, 1965 - 1970
  The following is a list of field office representatives for Latin America and the Caribbean for the years 1965 to 1970. The papers of Harry Wilhelm include memoranda and correspondence to and from these staff members:
  1965 Buenos Aires - John Nagel Santiago - John Nagel Rio de Janeiro - S. Widdicombe Mexico City - Robert Wickham Caracas - Robert Wickham Central America - Robert Wickham Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - Peter Fraenkel
  1966 Buenos Aires - John Nagel Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - S. Widdicombe Mexico City - William Gamble Central America - William Gamble Caracas - Roy Crawley Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - William Cotter
  1967 Buenos Aires - John Nagel Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - S. Widdicombe Mexico City - William Gamble Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - William Cotter Caribbean - John Hilliard
  1968 Buenos Aires - Richard Adams* Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - W. Carmichael Mexico City - William Gamble Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - William Cotter Jamaica - James Trowbridge*
  1969 Buenos Aires - Rey Carlson Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - W. Carmichael Mexico City - William Gamble Caribbean - William Gamble Central America - William Gamble Jamaica - James Trowbridge** Lima - Abe Lowenthal*** Bogota - William Cotter
  1970 Buenos Aires - Rey Carlson Santiago - Peter Bell Rio de Janeiro - W. Carmichael Mexico City - John Funari Caribbean - John Funari Central America - John Funari Jamaica - James Trowbridge** Lima - Richard Dye Bogota - William Gamble
  * Program Advisor ** Assistant Representative *** Acting Representative